The entertainment experience of a lifetime!
Ben-Hur is a history, drama, adventure film directed by William Wyler.
In 26 AD, Judah Ben-Hur, a Jew in ancient Judea,
opposes the occupying Roman empire.
Falsely accused by a Roman childhood friend-turned-overlord of trying to kill the Roman
governor, he is put into slavery and his mother and sister are taken away as prisoners.
Judah Ben-Hur, played by Charlton Heston.
Messala, played by Stephen Boyd.
Scheich Ildirim, played by Hugh Griffith.
Quintus Arrius, played by Jack Hawkins.
Esther, played by Haya Harareet.
Miriam, played by Martha Scott.
Ben-Hur () is a 1959 American religious epic film directed by William Wyler, produced
by Sam Zimbalist, and starring Charlton Heston as the title character.
A remake of the 1925 silent film with a similar title, it was adapted from
Lew Wallace's 1880 novel Ben-Hur: A Tale of the Christ.
The screenplay is credited to Karl Tunberg, but includes
contributions from Maxwell Anderson, S.
Behrman, Gore Vidal, and Christopher Fry.
The cast also features Stephen Boyd, Jack Hawkins, Haya Harareet, Hugh Griffith,
Martha Scott, Cathy O'Donnell in her final film, and Sam Jaffe.
Ben-Hur had the largest budget ($15.175 million), as well as the
largest sets built, of any film produced at the time.
Costume designer Elizabeth Haffenden oversaw a staff of 100 wardrobe fabricators to make the costumes, and a workshop
employing 200 artists and workmen provided the hundreds of friezes and statues needed in the film.
Filming commenced on May 18, 1958, and wrapped on January 7, 1959, with
shooting lasting for 12 to 14 hours a day and six days a week.
Pre-production began in Italy at Cinecittà around October
1957, and post-production took six months.
Under cinematographer Robert L.
Surtees, executives at Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer made the decision
to produce the film in a widescreen format.
Over 200 camels and 2,500 horses were used in the
shooting of the film, with some 10,000 extras.
The sea battle was filmed using miniatures in a huge tank on the back lot at
the Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studios in Culver City, California.
The nine-minute chariot race has become one of cinema's most famous action sequences, and the score, composed and conducted by Miklós
Rózsa, was at the time the longest ever composed for a film, and was highly influential on cinema for over 15 years.
Following a $14.7 million marketing effort, Ben-Hur premiered at Loew's
State Theatre in New York City on November 18, 1959.
It was the fastest-grossing as well as the highest-grossing film of 1959, becoming the
second highest-grossing film in history at the time, after Gone with the Wind.
It won a record eleven Academy Awards, including Best Picture, Best Director (Wyler), Best Actor in a Leading Role (Heston), Best Actor in a Supporting Role (Griffith), and Best
Cinematography – Color (Surtees); it also won Golden Globe Awards for Best Motion Picture – Drama, Best Director, and Best Supporting Actor – Motion Picture for Stephen Boyd.
In 1998, the American Film Institute named it the 72nd best American film and
the second best American epic film in the AFI's 10 Top 10.
In 2004, the National Film Preservation Board selected Ben-Hur for preservation by the National Film Registry
of the Library of Congress for being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of governor, middle east, based
on novel or book, roman empire, politics.
The tone is emotional.